all right greetings everyone
it's June 20th 2023 we're in our second
discussion on chapter six
so
we'll first just have any general
comments or anything
then we'll turn to the questions table
and look at what questions we didn't get
to last time and just kind of revisit
maybe condense
um some questions or just see what we
can do with with what is here so
anyone just want to make any general
comments on chapter six
uh I believe this is the second session
on chapter six right correct or maybe I
must okay yes
yeah
there was only one onboarding needed for
the welcome back here so we started one
week like faster into the Rhythm
um
okay so it looks like these were the
questions
I remember we left off with this one
let's just develop this into what was
um into a question that will continue to
continue on
okay
um
is there a common or good representation
or rubric
for about evaluating generative model
generative process
which is two generative models and
generative processes
anyone want to give a first thought or
just some other related questions
yeah well uh
go on please sorry no that's okay
uh yeah uh I I don't know I'm not sure
about uh what What's the exact criteria
for evaluating generative models
regenerative processes but uh one thing
is for sure that uh well I mean one of
the main right
at least uh when evaluating generative
model one of our main criteria should be
how uh closely uh
it tracks uh our
situation of interest and specifically
uh how relevant it is for addressing the
question that we're trying to
um I mean we're trying to examine so uh
it's not I I don't think it's something
a clear-cut or I don't know written
Stone and based on the context and the
situation
uh the evaluation criteria rubric should
be different I suppose both for
regenerative model and generous process
yeah so again we'll revisit this
generative model generative process
um question later following the recent
live stream but General process
working regenerative process as the
underlying uh process that gives rise to
the observations
this would seem to be more adequate to
the extent that it can better describe
the measurements
generative model
similarly is being evaluated based upon
its ability to to fit to the generative
process as well as
[Music]
um
phenomena of Interest
so not just to
um fit visual data but maybe to model
something like some illusion in visual
then
um there's a wide range of more General
statistical modeling techniques so first
is like the ultimate grab bag which is
just how relevant is the overall
modeling
um then there are statistical
evaluations of model adequacy and model
selection IQ information Criterion
Bayesian information Criterion base
Factor
um hierarchical likelihood ratio test if
you have a parametric model
bootstrap and non-parametric statistics
just general modeling and then
taking that more out of the statistics
into like the engineering
uh uh model life cycle
then that's where you can think about
validation verification validity
equality
Etc systems engineering model life cycle
any other thoughts or questions on this
Okay so
um I'm coming from um kind of an early
career data scientist background here
but um
I mean as far as
I mean what I find attractive about
active inference and doing things as
generative models is the attempt to you
know describe or explain what's going on
in the data and that being said um you
know in terms of a lot of mini
applications of like data science
machine learning
um
the emphasis upon is upon prediction and
so are these listed statistical metrics
you have here base Factor Bic Etc I mean
are those
basically like your error
measurements are they your
um
how to say
just attempt at measuring like accuracy
of prediction or
or is there some trade-off between
explainability and and prediction
if that makes sense
yeah
just to kind of summarize these
um so when you have nested parametric
models
then you can evaluate whether two models
are better in terms of including or not
some parametric factor and then testing
for their likelihood ratios
so this is a pretty straightforward test
but it's pretty limited to just strictly
nested parametric models so just just
getting that out of the way in general
we're in the Bayesian setting and so the
one of the advantages of the Bayesian
setting is that you can compare two
different models
that have totally different
architectures on the same data set so
one way that that's done is with this
aikiki information Criterion or the
Bayesian information Criterion
both of them do something very similar
which is they reward model fit and they
penalize the number of parameters so
actually in that way
it's a lot like
equation 2.5
you want to reward the fit but penalize
the complexity of the model
base factor is kind of like the hlrt but
it doesn't have to be ratios of nested
models you can just compare the relative
evidence in in favor of one a model or
another so this is used in structure
modeling and and uh structured learning
then in terms of but this is all like
kind of like testing amongst a portfolio
of models which ones are better
then how do you really get into the
space of like well how effective is this
model
um you could test on a new data set you
could do all the regular techniques like
cross validation leave one out Etc
or test on a new data set but then the
very interesting question is how do you
establish
the efficacy of an action model
because
um you know it's it's not just a passive
inference model so there you would need
to get into like benchmarks like the
open AI gym
and other
um
other settings where you can actually
test the efficacy of an action model
against some test input
rather than just a recognition model and
some input
but that gets so situational that there
aren't as as there's not like General
not there's not as many General
considerations there another strategy is
actually to even if it seems like a
passive inference problem like the mnist
digit data set
you could frame that in terms of the the
labeling is an action
so sometimes you can then take what
seems to be a passive inference problem
and then frame it as an active inference
problem
so then you don't need to worry about
these kind of like out-of-sample novel
context action models
you can just kind of use standard
benchmarks
and also as far as I know uh probably
the only serious work on benchmarking
the performance of active imprints
models
um is the work of
um theophy champion and his colleagues
branching time active inference which is
uh they've proposed several different
variants of branching time active
inference Each of which I mean with
increasing performance in terms of their
benchmarks and aside from that I'm not
aware of any other work that takes this
benchmarking study seriously enough to
to be reliable I guess
yeah surely there's a lot of proprietary
work in this area
um
the paper discussed in in um
live stream eight scaling active
inference
so here they they use like the kind of
um several standards
um testing environments
I forget what the pendulum
the hopper and then I think like the
mountain car or maybe maybe that's not
this one
but
they test the standards um
AI tests
all right
we're just looking just you know going
through the ones
all right are the transitions be
independent from the emissions
so for
[Music]
um
uh context
we're talking about figure 7.3 discrete
time active inference
are the transitions independent from the
emissions and what is the next
observation depend on
short answer
yes they're independent that's the
sparsity of the base graph so we can
clarify and give it a cleaner textual
answer but yes the conditional
independencies
which is the sparsity of the base graph
which allows us to do factorized
variational inference and get all of
these advantages
that's exactly what we're looking at
so this visual graphical model
is the sparsity architecture of the
conditional
um
independencies
so
yes
A and B are conditionally independent
conditionally independent based on what
hitting the state that's how Markov
blanket works
conditionally appended on the blanket A
and B are independent
that's true of all Bayesian graphs
so without worrying about the Markov
blanket and the interface and the
cybernetic agent and all of that
just
any node that intervenes between two
other nodes is the Markov blanket in
that setting
and then some other node you know
something else is blinking to get from
something else
but yes they're conditionally
independent what is the next observation
depend on
well
a matrix is the emission Matrix Tale of
Two densities it can emit from a hidden
state or it can recognize from an
observation
so any given observation is only
dependent upon the hidden State at that
time
and the hidden State at the next time
is only dependent upon the transition
Matrix
the transition Matrix
is uh has a slice for every action that
can be taken
every policy makes a slice in the B
tensor
so it's like
temperature in the room hidden State
thermometer observation
turn on the heater or not and there's
some B Matrix for the heater is on and
there's some B Matrix for the heater is
not on those are two slices in the same
object
and then policy selection means which
Matrix
which sub Matrix would be which slice of
B
should we multiply this to get to the
next time step
and then what observation would I expect
there
okay good good
um kind of standard question
okay what is the relevance of thinking
about good regulator theorem
for thinking about the generative model
so from cybernetics
good regular theorem originally stated
every good regulator of a system must be
a model of that system
or more accurately every good regulator
must contain a model of that system
here's a few quotes from a textbook
one way to approach this again these are
just all kind of big questions but we
can just see them many times what
happens to bad Regulators well
information processing sense making
decision making has a non-zero
informational cost
land hour limit there's a certain amount
of actual joules it takes to write and
erase
a bit it from bit Chris Fields
everything that is in that area so
information processing is never free
so in a dissipative and even adversarial
universe
to fail to regulate
is to fail to exist
how do we operationalize regulation in a
setting
that's going to be
revisiting
some non-equilibrium steady state
so if we're an observer looking at a
system
in order for us to measure it as diff as
signal relative to noise it has to be
persistently
re-measurable
over the background so we have to
repeatedly measure it
or an organism let's just say
can re-measure itself
so minimizing surprise about its
homeostatic temperature is being
adaptive
now if temperature were just flat and so
you could be unsurprised at homeostasis
by doing nothing
you'd get
lazy agents but if temperature was
really variable and contextual and there
was kind of these non-linear cues in the
environment and all of that
then in order to reduce surprise
about temperature
you'd end up
coming to effectively
have a model of the causal Nexus that
gives rise to observations
so the structure of the generative model
doesn't have to be the structure of the
generative process
however they may come to have certain
isomorphisms with each other
or at least statistical regularities
if there's actually a 24-hour cycle in
temperature
then you're going to see some kind of
oscillatory model in the generative
model
so
there's more to
um say there but oh and this is one good
note perhaps rather than good or bad
regulator the language of morality
or preference
the language should be accurate and
inaccurate
in effective and effective viable and
viable skillful unskillful so
there's always many ways to see it but
basically
if the generative model in the in the
limit case it just totally knows the
causal architecture of the world that's
the easiest way to be absolutely
unsurprised
and to have things as you expect slash
prefer is literally know how they're
going to play out
that's not plausible we use course
grading and approximations and
heuristics like variational inference
so the best we can do is just
iteratively optimize
towards bounding surprisal
so it's kind of like an empirical
optimizable heuristic for being a good
regulator
without getting too bogged down into
like the philosophy and the exactitude
the point is the ones that do well
enough to live live ones that don't do
well enough don't
but active inference is in the lineage
of cybernetics
so it's unsurprising that good regulator
theorem requisite diversity viable
systems models
a lot of things in the cybernetics
ontology have a natural home in the
active ontology
that they're you know they're talking
about the same territory adoptive agents
so it's not surprising that like they
don't invalidate each other or anything
like that
and actually I think uh it's one of the
reasons cybernetics
um
that experienced kind of revitalization
in recent years
especially in the past couple of years
so
yeah
all right how can organs others in the
brain be making inferences
so there's a few angles on this
the first
um or Ali or anyone else want to give a
thought
uh
one thing to point uh is this sense of
a kind of semi pan computationalism
that's been
um
if not time computationalism but but
something that bestows
um inference not only to complex
self-organizing systems such as the
brain but even to very simple linear
systems even a system as simple as an
inert to rock
uh so basically it's it it covers the
Spectrum there isn't I mean from the
point of view of fep there isn't
anything that's specifically unique
about the brain uh in other words the
same mathematical technology can be
applied uh both to inert rocks as well
as the uh the brain so
in my opinion this question should be
turned on its head and it's not that
how does inference can be seen in other
systems that are simpler systems but
rather
it should be I mean the relevant
question should be uh how does active
inference or the notion of inference
inactive inference literature applies to
all of those situations uh so one way to
do that is to define a kind of sparse
coupling between the environment and the
agent and define variational density as
the internal states of the system and
also obviously the external states of
the environment
would be the states that needs to be
tracked by those variational densities
and in this case there isn't anything
inherently different between the way the
brains uh or I don't know even sentient
agents uh
uh somehow undertake uh inference from
the way that the inert rocks and
partition and their states into internal
and external States but the main
difference would be the way the markup
blanket in those simpler systems can act
as as a kind of
statistical boundary that allows for
non-causal relationships I'm sorry
non-linear causal relationships as
opposed to
as a sorry linear causal relationships
as opposed to non-linear causal
relationships as observed in complex
agents or systems
so
yeah that's uh some of the main
distinctions between those
Michael awesome
yeah and then the classic paper that we
we often return to uh like Ali mentioned
the inner Rock
so this paper has the uh kind of visual
taxonomy
from simpler to more sophisticated
agents
um
sometimes the papers are in white
sometimes they're in Black
here
inert systems
active classical conservative systems
strange systems with World models of
their own and all of this
um just but but this is a great response
which is in a pan pan computationalist
or pan cognitivist or pain
inferentialist world then how does
active inference apply
one other angle is like let's just think
about the liver or the pancreas
and blood sugar that's our system of
Interest
realism is like is the pancreas actually
doing inference on blood sugar
and people can have a range of opinions
but in a pan cognitivist world the
answer is yes
or one can kind of pull back and just
say we're going to model the pancreas as
doing inference on blood sugar
so it's it is no different
it's just an interpretation of the same
statistical apparatus
basically
but there might be a setting where
um scientific realism is is more
Justified there's multiple lines of
conversion evidence
um the model is is
uh comprehensive
and so and being used to generate unique
explanations and predictions versus like
we're just going to do a linear
relationship between these two things in
the public health
and so then we're not going to confuse
the linear model with those with the
actual cause of architecture but there
are situations that you can design or
analyze
where the sparsity structure of the
system
which necessarily points to is what
grants to all these interesting
properties is becoming known to an
extent that Within
two or three or four Sigma it's like
we're starting to talk about how it is
not mistaking the map for the territory
that's the map territory fallacy
but also not doing some kind of map
denialism
which is the map territory fallacy
fallacy
and that's the paper which I'll add into
by Maxwell at all
and also if I may add another point
uh with regard to the distinction
between uh realism and instrumentalism
uh I believe
at least in the realism School uh
probably the most relevant or well
situated stance to uh
reframe active inference
I mean uh reframe its ontological status
is structural realism as argued by Majid
Benny and others in several papers
nice
yes
he's joined several discussions and it's
it's great to
um
okay is there some quotes from a book
but yes basically I
um forget organs other than the brain
how could anything be doing inference
and every and and then another angle to
take is just like the way that a
baseball uh computes a parabola
like
you don't need to think that it's doing
it like a calculator
but it but that's kind of like
naturalizing the computation that's a
path of least action in a spatial space
but also you could have a path of least
action in a cognitive space
that's Bayesian mechanics
and then you could have more realist or
more instrumentalist angle yeah yeah
please
uh sorry just one one thing that somehow
uh
I mean it gets confused is uh some
sometimes people think
FEPS claims that okay so if a
self-organism
I mean
if fep
formalism applies to a self-organizing
system then it should persist Through
Time by preserving its markup blankets
intact but
actually the claim of the fep is the
other way around so its main assertion
is that
if anything persists Through Time
how does fep applies to it so in other
sense fep doesn't provide any
justification per se for describing the
way that the system persists through
time but
we take the Persistence of the system
through time as the premise and then
apply fep to somehow
investigate the implications of that
premise through Bayesian mechanics and
fep formulas on
yeah
without the implicit or explicit
acknowledgment of the persistent
existence of what you're measuring or
yourself
you don't even have something to discuss
and a lot of times when people just
start to specify what they mean by like
the nouns and the verbs and the
adjectives they use
that's a deflationary approach
well what if there's something that
comes into being so so fast in between
moments and it's not being measured and
you can't detect it it's like well then
how do you know it's there
that's not within that statistical
sensing apparatus
so you have to take the existence of the
of the thing
to to be Primary in modeling something
an actual constant has a lot of work in
that area
could you please pull up The Path
integral paper on page four
if I may
sorry
yep
very nice thank you exactly right there
the fep addresses the following question
and it's like well if we're talking
about something that exists even in a
mental geometry
that's what we want we want to start
with
if it exists even hypothetically
so people say can it really describe all
things it's like well all the things
that exist or could exist we could use
this modeling approach to model
and talk about what properties it must
possess
but
if you're willing to open the door to
things that don't or can't exist
then of course this guy's limit on what
properties they do or don't possess
because they might it's like the you
know non-elephant animals things might
not exist for a huge variety of reasons
however things that exist either from an
external measure or measurement or from
self measurements
they must be acting as if they're
self-evidencing
reducing surprise relative to generative
model path of least action through an
information geometric space
if it isn't doing that you're not going
to observe it
and that's where we get the particular
partition
and the particular partition in the in
the particular physics
slash Bayesian mechanics
since Carl first since 2019 monograph a
free energy principle for a particular
physics that was like a big inflection
point
in this line of research
whereas in the 2016 to 2018
there's a lot of qualitative work and
the philosophical work applying to
multi-scale invested systems and and
self-organization
um amidst other empirical simulations
happening continually in all of this
so
reading reading works of different times
like different pieces are kind of going
to be made clear or not
what is the role of precision in nested
models
well here I'll uh and also by way of
demonstrating the the uh transferability
of active inference generative models
these three figures are discussed in
live stream 28 from the original paper
Smith at all computational phenomenology
so this is a static perceptual Bayesian
model
we have hidden State observations and we
hear
as a modulator literally a
neuromodulator on the a matrix Tail of
Two densities recognition Matrix
generated model
you have the Precision so Precision is
one over the temperature so whether you
think of it as like higher temperature
is lower Precision or lower you know or
vice versa
they're they're the same
when your Precision is low your
temperature is high
a gets blurred out
the high temperature limit is like a is
becomes flattened
whereas in the low temperature limit a
becomes sharpened
and so this is a common method in uh
recognition modeling okay
now they move into
adding action in so here there's the
policy figure 4.3 figure 7.3
everything we've looked at
and then they move to this
um nested model now in the Sanford Smith
paper it was being mobilized in terms of
basically phenomenology and meditative
experiences
direct sensory perception
you know visual perception and isaacades
attention
unreportable attention
and then awareness at a third level
observing that
and so the mo you you can add an
uncertainty like a Precision on any
variable you could have an uncertainty
on your prior D you could have
uncertainty on all kinds of things but
sometimes uncertainties on specific
variables
become associated with like certain
cognitive phenomena
in this case they're using it to
describe introspective
and explainable AI systems
taking the exact same figures exact same
formalisms just moving them into the AI
setting
so
um Precision on a and here's that live
stream 28 and the slides and everything
Precision on a is like sensory ambiguity
um
Precision on G so how how
precise are you on
the the free energy
um that is associated with the affect
in this uh sophisticated affect
here's some discussion on embodiment and
the Alexander technique
um so suffice to say
precision and nested modeling is
basically like the general Precision
concept which is basically used
everywhere this is how we fit Bayesian
models we have some hyper prior prior
Distribution on a parameter
and if that prior distribution is too
sharp then you're you're basically
that's a it's a pathology of the of the
prior it's too precise
if it was too imprecise
you have an underfit model
so it's like that and especially in
nested models
Precision plays a role in kind of gating
just in this case it's a general
question so you could make it do
anything basically but here the
Precision on a is like gating
let's just say the first and the third
level
so if there's no attention being paid to
sensory input
don't be surprised that they don't come
up to attention
but if the if this
um gating
can be like super direct and forceful
then you'll have propagation of
informational causality on this network
up to the higher level
h113 in the textbook
all right the decision so this is about
planning as inference which one of these
questions
um was also about
the decision whether to model
alternative futures
counter factual features conditions upon
policy selection how would the world
change if I did this or that is largely
tied up with the choice between discrete
and continuous models
because the idea of selecting between
alternative Futures defined by sequences
of actions is more simply articulated
using discrete time models all right
so
figure 4.3
figure 4.3 is like the Rosetta Stone it
juxtaposes the discrete time continuous
discrete time generative model and the
continuous time generative model
so I'll just copy this
in the discrete time model you have S T
minus 1 s of t s of t plus one so
Futures and pasts if it's sophisticated
active inference are being explicitly
modeled
so it's like what would happen at seven
o'clock if I did this
that is explicitly addressable with a
discrete time model of the correct time
Horizon
so you have to explicitly say I'm
talking about an hourly model and seven
depth and so then you in branching time
active inference just like a chess
algorithm it's dealing with like the
branching
structure because if you have a lot of
affordances
then then you have and you have a lot of
time depth you can imagine this this is
a combinatorial explosion
um in contrast
though these two generative models are
shown here to emphasize their structural
similarity
The Continuous time generative model is
actually not explicitly modeling past
present future time steps
rather it's modeling the generalized
coordinates of motion x hidden State X
prime rate of change X double Prime
second derivative
so in that way it's a lot more like a
Taylor series expansion
so a Taylor series expansion technically
even a Taylor series expansion of you
know depth one
it has an answer for every single point
in the number line
but that doesn't mean it's a good one
um and so the continuous time models
kind of trivially have something to say
about all possible time steps
just by analytic continuation of the
Taylor series expansion in the
generalized coordinates emotion away
however
you don't necessarily like know how
accurate it is for any given points
it also doesn't
have explicit counterfactuals
so if you do some Taylor series
expansion it says yeah at x equals three
over Y is 5.
but then if you said well what if it
were different
the only way you could do that would be
change the parameters of the Taylor
series and recalculate it at that point
so the model itself is not exactly doing
these like what would happen if I did
that
so Futures are explicit
in discrete time models
and interpretable explicitly
whereas in continuous time models pasts
and Futures are kind of trivially
predicted
such that it doesn't really make sense
to talk about just um counterfactuals in
the same exact way
and these models can be hybridized and
and fused
which is in um chapter eight
can we generate a a code template looks
like yes but there's of course more
information
but it's an important question
how is temporal depth specific to
planning does temporal depth in
perception make any sense
what is temporal depth
so temporal depth is how many time steps
are the models considered in the
discrete time case
um this temporal depth make sense in
perception
well perception is always modeled as
instantaneous
however depending on the temporal scale
of of a model
that perception may be instantaneous
over a certain temporal thickness
power Y is temporal depth specific to
planning
so in planning as inference policy
selection is inference your selecting or
sampling from policies based upon their
expected free energy
in order to plan over a given time
Horizon and actually evaluate
the um
the play outs you need to have a
temporal depth of that amount
Thomas Parr in his
um book stream
so early implementations were coming
from the filtering of a generalized
filtering approach maybe it wasn't
generalized at that point but particle
filtering approach and I equipped these
models with action
then people started thinking about how
to get sequential Dynamics Predator prey
lock of Volterra models winnerless
competition neural Darwinism
in these situations there's in aversions
of sequential
recurrent continuous Dynamics like a
limit cycle of more than two
then people wanted to model explicit
long-term planning
and so from around
you know
2014 or something
there was a lot more development in the
discrete State space model which enabled
the well understood partially observable
bar composition process
and a lot of the characterization of the
planning as inference explore exploit
um
then
later developments supported
um nested models here there's a discrete
time on top and a discrete time on the
bottom but also it could be continuous
time on the bottom
oh yes then continuous State models were
reintroduced
as the lower levels of higher level
discrete time models
and um that is kind of like the folk
psychology live stream 46 active
inference does not contradict folk
psychology
discrete time decision making up top
you know discrete time and discrete
decisions
and then more on the sensory motor it's
more like continuous time continuous
action
okay
new question
figure 6.1
all right
particular partition
how is the mutual interaction between
active States and sensory States meant
in six one so the bi-directional line
here
can they mutually change their states
without impacting neither internal nor
external States
yes they could
you could have
um nodes that
are these nodes are in communication
with each other
in general this image it's more
important what it what it doesn't show
so there's no backwards Arrow from
external to octave or from internal to
sensory you can't have your thumb on the
scale
and the symmetry of whatever that is
from the outside
and the only other constraint is no
telepathy no telekinesis
the only way to receive information
about external States is through sensory
States the only way to act on costly
intervene on external States is through
active States so
no thumb on the scale and the mirror
no telepathy no telekinesis
that doesn't mean that for any given
model these arrows are like all
important or all relative uh or I mean
all relatively the same importance
so if you want to design a computer
system where the sensory States comes in
one computer and this is a second
computer and this is the third computer
so like there's no direct Edge between
sensory and active States
that's you can create that causal
architecture
what is it supposed to model nothing
modeling of supposed things is done in
chapter six and Beyond but in general
this is not trying to model any specific
situation despite the brain in the world
could they Circle Mutual mutually
modifying their states and then
eventually arrive at a state where they
change the external internal States
yeah maybe they have a faster time scale
or something or maybe they're in
communication with each other
and then active States ends or like
sensory States ends up influencing
internal States via active influencing
it and so yes it could happen would that
mean that we can model with this trick
any arbitrary Behavior
it's not necessarily a trick it's just a
particular partition
without allow us to model terrain
equivalence
I'm not sure
if there's an understanding of what
formally demonstrates turn equivalence
then I I but I believe it's possible I
think as a turing architecture as far as
I understand it abstracted from the Von
Neumann architecture is basically just
saying like you can do a touring tape
so I don't see why not
why would we need that
512k ought to be enough for anyone right
I don't know why we need it
we expect it
but yeah the these graphs in general are
more like
the space of the possible
with the important caveats of that were
mentioned with the no thumb on the scale
and the mirror and the natural empathy
note telekinesis
but how relevant these edges are or what
systems have what Behavior or what
cognitive phenomena are granted by what
Dynamics on graphs
there's just no General answer to those
things because if you do a graph
for one setting it's going to be
different
what did you mean
when you said that any entree could be
ordered with any side dish
like that in this recipe theme that
we're in
models that include continuous or
discrete variables or both
what is meant by variable States or
observations how can States be
continuous
as those here are probably familiar with
States or observations could be like
discrete like zero or one
or any integer or it could be a
continuous number
computers discretize continuous
functions to approximate them
but there's so many exciting directions
with unconventional Computing analog
Computing mem computing
Etc
that like
there's more to it but just simply it
could be any type of variable
okay like this new new question this is
this is um
let's maybe look at this one in closing
if the external state is unknowable how
can we set up a generative process
so that's what's generating the
observations when our experience is
based solely on
the process of reducing variational free
energy based on predictions and sensory
inputs across the markup blanket
this person has just described the
challenge of life
I don't think that there's a specific
answer to that I think this is literally
a restatement of the particular
partition
if this was just said
um the challenge is based is to given
the unknowability direct unknowability
of unturned States The Challenge and the
opportunity is to set up a generative
model based solely on the process of
reducing free energy based on
predictions and sensory inputs across a
blanket and adaptive action
I'm not sure if they meant process or
model here
because setting up a generative process
is something that the human modeler does
when they're designing a simulation but
not like what the um
animal has to do
what I'm trying to get at here is we are
making an assumption about the generator
sensory input when making the model
yes
but that model can never be accurate
well it absolutely can be accurate it's
never going to be a one-to-one map as
the territory
but of course it can be accurate we
don't need to understand I have an
atomic simulation of the sun to have a
generative process of how many photons
are going to hit my window tomorrow at
7am
so there's a core invalidity in the
notion that we set up a generative
process model
not sure what ontology mixing is
happening but almost by definition we're
introducing an error in the model by
setting up the parameters
for the generative process the general
model we remove the fundamental of
aspect of actin which is the dynamical
system has only one thing you can do and
that's to reduce free energy
so there's some some good points and
some mixed things so
um
it's not what it does is the action it
takes in the world variational free
energy is just a tractable computational
heuristic
yes if you set up
the generative process to be a number
continuous number between one and ten
and then the generative model to do the
exact same to kind of have
pre-structurally learned the problem
then it's going to be a simple
simulation
whereas you can have a more
sophisticated simulation that involves
structure learning as part of the
agent's generative model
are we not introducing information the
model that would not be available in the
real world if we actually defined the
generative process yeah you can give any
model too much information essentially
so if it has if the model actually knows
what is really happening then you know
like if you were doing a um video game
and it and you had a agent with
supervisory access to the other players
inferences or even control their actions
yeah
that's not going to work in a tournament
but here with a particular partition we
can actually know the information
encapsulation
and Majid Benny explores that in terms
of the partial information encapsulation
so are we not introducing information to
model that would not be available
it's your restaurant
do whatever you got to do with the
recipe if you want a pedagogical example
that just
make some clean graphs and is very
straightforward and doesn't engage the
complexities of like sophisticated
cognitive structure learning
that model is not going to complain if
you want to do
strange Loop reflexive structure
modeling for ambiguous inputs of
unstructured multimodal data Etc
then that is your challenge
so for many people it's just in one
closing comment and many people this is
the first time they've been exposed to
statistical modeling and iterative
modeling formally
so that's why there are often questions
that are like less about active
inference
but sometimes crop up about basically
using statistical modeling overall which
is a great thing because these are
challenging and and areas with a lot of
implicit and tacit knowledge
so
thank you fellows
looking forward to
uh next discussions and into uh heading
into chapter seven
next week Ali maybe we'll do a um
maybe we'll do our DOT zero for chapter
seven and eight but not in a hurry but
we'll figure it out
sure
thank you so much thank you thank you
bye